<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - Unit Upgrades for Civilopedia -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_INDIAN_FAST_WORKER</Tag>
		<Russian>Пенджабский работник</Russian>
		<English>Punjabi Worker</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Ouvrier du Panjвb</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Pandschabischer Bautrupp</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Lavoratore del Punjab:Lavoratori del Punjab</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Trabajador de Panyab:Trabajadores de Panyab</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<!--
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MALI_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Malinese Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire malien</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Malinesisches Reich:Malinesische Reich:Malinesischen Reich</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Malinese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Malн</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CHINA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Chinese Empire</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Empire chinoise</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Chinesisches Kaiserreich:Chinesische Kaiserreich:Chinesischen Kaiserreich</Text>
			<Gender>Neuter:Neuter:Neuter</Gender>
			<Plural>0:0:0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Impero Cinese</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Imperio Chino</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_INCAN_QUECHUA</Tag>
		<Russian>Воик Кечуа</Russian>
		<English>Quechua Warrior</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Guerrier quechua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Quechua Krieger</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Guerriero quechua:Guerrieri quechua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Guerrero quechua:Guerreros quechua</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ROME_PRAETORIAN</Tag>
		<Russian>Легионер</Russian>
		<English>Legion</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Lйgion</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Legion</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Legion:Legioni</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Legiуn:Legiones</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MODERN_ARMOR</Tag>
		<Russian>Основной боевой танк</Russian>
		<English>Main Battle Tank</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Char de combat principal</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Kampfpanzer</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Carro da combattimento:Carri da combattimento</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Tanque de combate principal:Tanques de combate principal</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- name of Phalanx changed by Leoreth -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GREEK_PHALANX</Tag>
		<Russian>Гоплит</Russian>
		<English>Hoplite</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Hoplite</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Hoplit</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Oplita:Opliti</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Hoplita:Hoplitas</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ROME_PRAETORIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<Russian>[TAB]The Roman Legions, created during the early wars of the Republic and tested during the three Punic Wars against Carthage, were the fighting force that conquered and held the Roman Empire together for five centuries. Each legion was composed of 6000 men, divided into 60 smaller groups known as centuries. Nearly unstoppable on the attack, the legion was relatively weak on defense. The legion's demise as a military unit was accelerated by the destruction of Emperor Valens' army by gothic knights in the fourth century.</Russian>
		<English>[TAB]The Roman Legions, created during the early wars of the Republic and tested during the three Punic Wars against Carthage, were the fighting force that conquered and held the Roman Empire together for five centuries. Each legion was composed of 6000 men, divided into 60 smaller groups known as centuries. Nearly unstoppable on the attack, the legion was relatively weak on defense. The legion's demise as a military unit was accelerated by the destruction of Emperor Valens' army by gothic knights in the fourth century.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les lйgions romaines, crййes lors des guerres de la Rйpublique et mises а l'йpreuve au cours des trois guerres puniques contre Carthage, sont la force militaire qui a permis а Rome de conquйrir, puis de prйserver son Empire pendant cinq siиcles. Chaque lйgion se composait de 6 000 hommes, rйpartis en 60 unitйs appelйes centuries. Quasiment invincible en attaque, la lйgion йtait relativement faible en dйfense. La disparition de la lйgion a йtй accйlйrйe au IVe siиcle par la dйfaite de l'armйe de l'Empereur Valens contre la cavalerie des Goths.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die rцmischen Legionen wurden wдhrend der frьhen Kriege der Republik Rom ins Leben gerufen und stellten ihr Kцnnen zuerst in den drei Punischen Kriegen gegen Karthago unter Beweis. Im GroЯen und Ganzen ist es letztlich ihnen zu verdanken, dass das Rцmische Reich ein derartig groЯes Territorium erobern und mehr als fьnfhundert Jahre lang auch zusammenhalten konnte. Jede Legion bestand aus insgesamt 6.000 Mann, die sich in 60 kleinere Truppenverbдnde, die so genannten Zenturien, gliederten. Die Offensivkraft einer Legion war nahezu unьbertroffen, allerdings wies ihre Verteidigung relativ groЯe Schwдchen auf. Ausschlaggebend fьr die endgьltige Abschaffung der Legionen als Militдreinheiten war die Vernichtung der Armee des rцmischen Kaisers Valens durch die gotischen Ritter im 4. Jahrhundert.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Le Legioni Romane, create durante i primi anni della Repubblica e messe alla prova durante le tre Guerre Puniche contro Cartagine, rappresentavano la forza militare dell'Impero Romano, che durт la bellezza di cinque secoli. Ciascuna legione era composta da 6.000 uomini, divisi in 60 gruppi piщ piccoli, denominati centurie. La Legione era inarrestabile in attacco, ma debole quando si trattava di difendere. La fine di questa unitа militare venne dichiarata con la distruzione dell'esercito dell'Imperatore Valente per mano dei cavalieri barbari, durante il quarto secolo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Las legiones romanas, creadas durante las primeras guerras de la Repъblica y puestas a prueba durante las tres Guerras Pъnicas contra Cartago, eran las fuerzas bйlicas que conquistaron y mantuvieron unido el Imperio Romano durante cinco siglos. Cada legiуn se componнa de seis mil hombres, divididos en sesenta grupos mбs pequeсos llamados centurias. Casi imparable cuando atacaba, la legiуn era relativamente dйbil en cuanto a defensa. El fin de la legiуn como unidad militar se acelerу por la destrucciуn del ejйrcito del emperador Valentiniano por los caballeros godos en el siglo IV.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_INCAN_QUECHUA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<Russian>[TAB]The Incan Quechua warriors were fierce South American warriors who in the period between 1440 and 1530 conquered much of the Andes and coastal regions of what is now Peru and Ecuador. These lightly-armed and fast-moving infantry were equipped with a variety of clubs, including light throwing clubs and heavy crushing weapons similar in design to maces. The Quechua were also quite proficient with the "bola," two balls attached by twine, which they used with great effect to bring down birds and small game.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Inca were overwhelmed and destroyed in the mid-16th Century by the Spanish Conquistadors. Though an extremely small force, the Spaniards were equipped with muskets, horsemen and cannon, fearsome weapons that the Incans had never encountered before. Unlike many other Native American nations, the Incans resisted the Spanish; but once again the Conquistadors made great use of its enemy's internal divisions, encouraging many subject tribes to rise up and turn on their Incan masters.</Russian>
		<English>[TAB]The Incan Quechua warriors were fierce South American warriors who in the period between 1440 and 1530 conquered much of the Andes and coastal regions of what is now Peru and Ecuador. These lightly-armed and fast-moving infantry were equipped with a variety of clubs, including light throwing clubs and heavy crushing weapons similar in design to maces. The Quechua were also quite proficient with the "bola," two balls attached by twine, which they used with great effect to bring down birds and small game.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Inca were overwhelmed and destroyed in the mid-16th Century by the Spanish Conquistadors. Though an extremely small force, the Spaniards were equipped with muskets, horsemen and cannon, fearsome weapons that the Incans had never encountered before. Unlike many other Native American nations, the Incans resisted the Spanish; but once again the Conquistadors made great use of its enemy's internal divisions, encouraging many subject tribes to rise up and turn on their Incan masters.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les Quechuas incas йtaient de fйroces guerriers d'Amйrique du Sud qui, entre 1440 et 1530, conquirent une grande partie des Andes et des rйgions cфtiиres (actuels Pйrou et Equateur). Ces fantassins, lйgиrement armйs mais trиs mobiles, йtaient йquipйs de massues de diffйrentes sortes : certaines йtaient lйgиres et pouvaient кtre lancйes, d'autres йtaient lourdes et ressemblaient а des masses. Les Quechuas maniaient aussi le "bola," une arme de jet formйe de deux boules attachйes par une laniиre, qu'ils utilisaient pour chasser les oiseaux ou le petit gibier.[PARAGRAPH:1]L'empire Inca fut anйanti au milieu du XVIe siиcle par les conquistadors espagnols. Bien que peu nombreux, ceux-ci disposaient de mousquets, de chevaux et de canons, armes terrifiantes totalement inconnues des Incas. A la diffйrence de nombreuses autres civilisations indiennes d'Amйrique, les Incas rйsistиrent aux Espagnols, mais ces derniers surent exploiter les divisions internes de leurs ennemis, encourageant les tribus soumises а se soulever et а attaquer leurs maоtres Incas.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Quechua-Inka waren ein sьdamerikanisches Kriegervolk, das zwischen 1440 und 1530 weite Teile der Anden und die Kьstenregionen im heutigen Peru und Ecuador eroberten. Diese schnelle, leicht bewaffnete Infanterie war mit Knьppeln, leichten Wurfkeulen und schweren Streitkolben bewaffnet. Darьber hinaus waren die Quechua Meister der "Bola", zweier Kugeln, mit denen sie Vцgel und kleinere Tiere erlegten.[PARAGRAPH:1]Mitte des 16. Jahrhunderts wurden die Inka von den spanischen Konquistadoren ьberwдltigt und ausgelцscht. Die Spanier waren Wenige, aber mit Musketen, Reitern und Kanonen ausgerьstet. Im Gegensatz zu vielen anderen Vцlkern des amerikanischen Kontinents leisteten die Inka den Spaniern Widerstand. Doch die Konquistadoren nutzten innere Streitigkeiten unter den Indianerstдmmen geschickt aus und ermutigten diese, sich gegen die Inka zu erheben.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]I guerrieri quechua inca erano dei fieri guerrieri sudamericani che conquistarono la maggior parte delle Ande e delle regioni costiere tra Ecuador e Perщ, tra il 1440 e il 1530. Queste unitа di fanteria erano rapide e dotate di armamenti leggeri, come bastoni; una delle loro armi ricordava una grossa mazza. I Quechua erano molto abili nell'uso delle "bola", due sfere tenute insieme da una corda, molto utili per prendere uccelli e piccola cacciagione.[PARAGRAPH:1]Gli Inca vennero sopraffatti e distrutti dai conquistadores Spagnoli verso la metа del 16&#176; secolo. Malgrado fossero in inferioritа numerica, gli Spagnoli erano equipaggiati con moschetti, cavalli e cannoni, armi temibili che gli Inca non avevano mai visto prima. Al contrario di altre popolazioni native americane, gli Inca resistettero agli Spagnoli. Ma ancora una volta i conquistadores sfruttarono le fratture interne alla societа e incoraggiarono molte tribщ a ribellarsi contro i loro dominatori Inca.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los incas quechua eran unos feroces guerreros sudamericanos que, entre 1440 y 1530, conquistaron gran parte de los Andes y las regiones costeras de lo que es hoy Perъ y Ecuador. Esta infanterнa ligera y rбpida estaba equipada con una variedad de garrotes, incluyendo unos ligeros que se lanzaban y otros pesados de diseсo parecido a mazas. Eran tambiйn muy hбbiles con la "bola", dos pelotas conectadas con bramante que usaban con gran pericia para matar pбjaros y caza menor.[PARAGRAPH:1]Los incas fueron doblegados y destruidos a mitad del siglo XVI por los conquistadores espaсoles. Aunque extremadamente pequeсos en nъmero, los espaсoles estaban equipados con mosquetes, jinetes y caсones, armas temibles a las que los incas nunca se habнan enfrentado. A diferencia de muchas otras naciones indнgenas de Amйrica, los incas resistieron a los espaсoles, pero una vez mбs, los conquistadores aprovecharon bien las divisiones internas de sus enemigos, animando a muchas tribus a sublevarse contra sus amos incas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
