<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DAWN_OF_MAN_SCREEN_TITLE</Tag>
		<Russian>Рассвет цивилизации</Russian>
		<English>DAWN OF A CIVILIZATION</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_EGYPT</Tag>
		<Russian>3000 год до н.э. В результате объединения Нижнего и Верхнего Египта образуется египетская цивилизация. Плодородные берега Нила делают Египет одним из богатейших регионов мира. Пришло время использовать эти богатсва, чтобы построить монументы и создать культуру, которые еще не видел мир.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. The Egyptian civilization coalesces under the recent unification of the Kingdoms of Lower and Upper Egypt. The fertile banks of the Nile make Egypt one of the wealthiest regions of the world. It is time to use this wealth to build monuments and establish a culture the world has never seen before.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_INDIA</Tag>
		<Russian>1500 год до н.э. После падения цивилизации Хараппы, ведические арийцы достигли Индо-Гангской равнины. Последующая ведическая эра характеризовалась развитием кастовой системы и образованием королевств Махаджанапады, в которых были созданы наиболее важные эпосы индийской культуры, ставшие основой превращения Индии в религиозный и духовный центр мира.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1500 BC. After the collapse of the Harappan civilization, the Vedic Aryans reach the Indo-Gangetic plain. The following Vedic era features the development of a caste system and the Mahajanapada kingdoms, where the most important epics of Indian culture are authored, laying the foundation to transform India into the religious and spiritual center of the world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_INDIA_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Sixteen years ago, Shivaji Bhosle has established the Maratha Kingdom, the first Hindu state to challenge Mughal hegemony over Northern India. With Mughal power declining, now is the time to break Muslim domination of the subcontinent for good.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CHINA</Tag>
		<Russian>3000 год до н.э. Китай является самым восточным из регионов мира, в которых впервые зародилась цивилизация. Во времена династий Ся, Шан и Чжоу, когда города развивались, в основном, в окрестностях Желтой реки (Хуанхе), была изобретена концепция "Мандата Небес", призванная узаконить правление Срединного царства на протяжении веков.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. China is the easternmost region of the world where human civilization first develops. Through the dynasties of Xia, Shang and Zhou, cities develop mainly in the vicinity of the Yellow River, and the concept of a "Mandate of Heaven" is invented to legitimize the rule of the Middle Kingdom of China through the ages.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CHINA_LATE</Tag>
		<Russian>600 год н.э. После падения династии Хань, последовала гражданская война между китайскими королевствами. Лишь 11 лет назад Императору Ян Цзянь(в начале правления  Суй Вэнь-ди) удалось заново объединить Китай и вернуть Мандат Небес. Но сила династии Суй ещ¸ не полностью объединены, а прежние вызовы остаются для Китая актуальными.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. After the Han Dynasty had collapsed, civil war between the Chinese kingdoms ensued. Only 11 years ago Emperor Wen of Sui managed to reunite China and reclaim the Mandate of Heaven. But the power of the Sui Dynasty is not completely consolidated, and the old challenges of China remain.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CHINA_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. After the Ming Dynasty has collapsed under peasant revolts, the Jurchens of Manchuria have conquered China and established the Qing Dynasty. With Manchuria, Xinjiang and Tibet under imperial control, China has reached the greatest extent in history, and the rule of the Kangxi Emperor promises another golden era.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BABYLONIA</Tag>
		<Russian>3000 год до н.э. Плодорный полумесяц Междуречья стал домом для первых городских культур в истории человечества и колыбелью цивилизации. Хотя города Шумера и &#192;ккада процветают, с появлением Вавилона, они вскоре были затмены величайшым городом своего времени.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. The fertile crescent of Mesopotamia is home of the first urbanized cultures in the history of mankind and known as the cradle of civilization. Though the cities of Sumer and Akkad are thriving, with the emergence of Babylon, they will soon be overshadowed by the greatest metropolis of its time.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_HARAPPA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 3000 BC. The river beds of the Indus and Sarasvati provide fertile ground for ancient civilization. With unparalleled sanitation and urban planning, the Indus Valley Civilization centered around the city of Harappa can make use of this fertility and become the most widespread and populous civilization of its time.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_GREECE</Tag>
		<Russian>1600 год до н.э. Первые города-государства появляются на Греческом полуострове. Хотя разделение греческой цивилизации может показаться на первый взгляд недостатком, но акцент на независимости поощерял появление новых идей в литературе, науке и философии, а также новых тактик в искустве войны.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1600 BC. The first city states emerge on the Greek peninsula. While the division of the Greek civilization might seem as a disadvantage at first, their emphasis on independence favors the inception of new ideas in literature, science and philosophy as well as new tactics in the art of warfare.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PERSIA</Tag>
		<Russian>844 год до н.э. Персия всегда была родиной воинственных людей, но теперь династия &#192;хеменидов объединила их в организованную империю. Хотя Иранское нагорье не очень богато, у него есть богатые и беззащитные соседи в Индии на востоке и в Междуречье на западе, которых можно завоевать, чтобы стать крупнейшей империей мира.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 844 BC. Persia has always been home to warlike peoples, but now the Achaemenid dynasty provides them with the unifying force to form an organized empire. While the Persian plateau is not particularly wealthy, it has rich and defenseless neighbors in India in the east and Mesopotamia in the west to conquer on their way to become the world's greatest empire.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PERSIA_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. The Safavid Dynasty, which has ruled Persia since 1500 AD, is losing authority over its territory. The time is ripe for a competent warlord to seize control and humiliate the neighboring Turks, Uzbeks and Mughals ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PHOENICIA</Tag>
		<Russian>1200 год до н.э. Внешние вторжения ослабили царства Междуречья, что позволило Финикийским городам-государствам получить независимость. Так как соседние земли управлялись более мощными цивилизациями, финикийцы обратили свои взгляды на запад, увидя возможность богатеть за счет торговли на Средиземном море.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1200 BC. Foreign invasions have weakened the Mesopotamian kingdoms, allowing the Phoenician city states to achieve independence. With the neighboring lands dominated by more powerful civilizations, the Phoenicians have turned their eyes to the west, seeing the opportunity to gain wealth by trade on the Mediterranean Sea.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_POLYNESIA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1000 BC. Polynesian settlers have migrated to the Tongan and Samoan islands. With their exceptional navigational skills, they can reach and settle even the most isolated islands in the South Pacific Ocean around them.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ROME</Tag>
		<Russian>752 год до н.э., латины только что основали Рим. Он расположен в благоприятном месте, имеет превосходную политическую системой: ему суждено контролировать весь &#192;пеннинский полуостров. Большинство соседних регионов Европы остаются варварскими и нецивилизованными. Карфаген - его единственный соперник на пути к правлению всем Средиземноморьем.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 753 BC. The Latin people have just founded the city of Rome. Situated at a favorable position and governed by a superior political system, it is fated to control the whole Italian peninsula. Most of its neighboring regions in Europe are still barbaric and uncivilized. The city of Carthage is its only rival on the way to rule and civilize the whole Mediterranean.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_JAPAN</Tag>
		<Russian>525 год н.э. В ранние японские государства, централизующиеся вокруг провинции Ямато, из Кореи распространился Буддизм. Это позволило распространить влияние династий Суй и Тан на Японию, за чем последовала централизация сил в Японскую Империю.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 525 AD. The early Japanese polity centered around the Yamato province is introduced to Buddhism from Korea. This allows the spread of Chinese influences from the Sui and Tang dynasties to Japan, followed by a centralization of power into the Empire of Japan.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_JAPAN_LATE</Tag>
		<Russian>600 год н.э. В ранние японские государства, централизующиеся вокруг провинции Ямато, из Кореи распространился Буддизм. Это позволило распространить влияние династий Суй и Тан на Японию, за чем последовала централизация сил в Японскую Империю.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. The early Japanese polity centered around the Yamato province is introduced to Buddhism from Korea. This allows the spread of Chinese influences from the Sui and Tang dynasties to Japan, followed by a centralization of power into the Empire of Japan.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_JAPAN_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Under the Tokugawa Shogunate, Japan has been at peace for almost a century now. But contact with European traders threatens to disturb the achieved balance again, and even the complete seclusion under the Sakoku cannot preserve it forever. Japan will have to open itself to the world ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ETHIOPIA</Tag>
		<Russian>295 год до н.э. Эфиопское нагорье является исключительно плодородным из-за умеренного климата, но оно очень удалено от других цивилизаций. Ситуация изменилась, когда основные торговые пути между Римской Империей и Индией сместились в Красное море, что позволило разцвести эфиопскому королевству &#192;ксум.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 295 BC. The Ethiopian highlands are exceptionally fertile due to its temperate climate, but also quite remote from other civilizations. This changes when the major trade routes between the Roman Empire and Indians shift to the Red Sea, allowing the Ethiopian kingdom of Aksum to flourish.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_KOREA</Tag>
		<Russian>50 год до н.э. На корейском полуострове формируются три корейских царства: Силла, Пэкче и Когуре, это первый шаг к централизации власти над бывшими вождествами. Китайцы находятся близко, Корее прид¸тся освоить их более совершенную организацию, не потеряв при этом суверенитета.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 50 BC. The three Korean kingdoms of Silla, Baekje and Goguryeo form on the Korean peninsula, the first step of centralization of power away from their predecessor chiefdoms. The Chinese are close; Korea will have to have to adapt their more advanced organization without abandoning its own sovereignty.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_KOREA_LATE</Tag>
		<Russian>600 год н.э. Три корейских царства по прежнему процветают, а Когуре распространяет влияние корейской цивилизации в Маньчжурию. Но так как Китай снова объединился, они должны защищать свою независимость.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. The three Korean kingdoms still thrive and Goguryeo has expanded the influence of Korean civilization into Manchuria. But now that China is reunited again, they have to be careful to protect their independence for the future.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_KOREA_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. The Kingdom of Joseon has faced both invasion from Japan and the Manchu, who now control the entire Chinese Empire. Now a period of relative peace and economic and cultural renaissance has begun, but with two powerful neighbors and Western imperialism on the rise, it can only last for so long ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MAYA</Tag>
		<Russian>60 год н.э. Появление городов на полуострове Юкатан дало стимул образованию городов-государств майя, чьи технологические и архитектурные достижения создали первую развитую цивилизацию в &#192;мериках.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 60 AD. Urbanization on the peninsula of Yucatan sparks the formation of the Mayan city states, whose technological and architectural advancements would create the first advanced civilization in the Americas.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BYZANTIUM</Tag>
		<Russian>330 год н.э. Римской Империи с востока угрожают вторжения варваров, становится очевидным, что Рим не может управлять Империей в одиночку. Константин Великий основывает Константинополь как "Новый Рим", в надежде, что Восточная Империя сможет противостоять этим вторжениям и когда-нибудь возродить славу Римской Империи.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 330 AD. With the Roman Empire threatened by Barbarian invasions from the east, it becomes evident that the Empire cannot be governed from Rome alone. So Constantine the Great has founded Constantinopolis as a "New Rome", in hopes that the Eastern Empire will be able to withstand these incursions and eventually restore the glory of the Roman Empire.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BYZANTIUM_LATE</Tag>
		<Russian>600 год н.э. После смерти Юстиниана, большая часть его достижений была утрачена. Ломбарды взяли Северную Италию, а Дунай вряд ли может сдержать славян, а Византия ввергнута в Войну против  Персии Сасанидов. Победа в этой войне оказалась пирровой, а Империя теперь ослаблена в экономическом и военном отношениях.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. After the death of Justinian, most of his successes have been unmade again. While the Lombards took Northern Italy and the Danube could be barely held against the Slavs, Byzantium was also plunged into a war against Sassanid Persia. Its victory proved Pyrrhic, and now the Empire is economically and militarily weakened.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_VIKINGS</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 551 AD. The scarcity of food makes the inhabitants of Scandinavia excellent sailors that rely on fishing and trade. Their home kingdoms still can't sustain further population growth, and the Vikings have to turn to lands across the sea. Not only the coasts of the North Sea, but also the Mediterranean and even the New World make good targets for plunder or settlement.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_VIKINGS_LATE</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 600 AD. The scarcity of food makes the inhabitants of Scandinavia excellent sailors that rely on fishing and trade. Their home kingdoms still can't sustain further population growth, and the Vikings have to turn to lands across the sea. Not only the coasts of the North Sea, but also those of the Mediterranean and even the New World make good targets for either plunder or settlement.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SWEDEN_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. The Kingdom of Sweden is the most formidable of the Scandinavian powers and has managed to establish an empire by acquiring Finland. Still, its expansion has also created enemies, and rivals like Denmark-Norway, Poland and especially Russia might seek to curb Swedish power ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ARABIA</Tag>
		<Russian>622 год н.э. Ислам объединил арабские народы под знаменем Халифата. Непосредственные соседи &#192;равии (Византийская Империя и Сасанидская Персия) ослаблены их недавними войнами. Это подходящее время для распространения Ислама на их богатые владения, формирующий плавильный котел для культур, который вознесет культуру и науку на новые высоты.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 622 AD. The founding of Islam unites the Arabian people under the banner of the Caliphate. Arabia's direct neighbors, the Byzantine Empire and Sassanid Persia, are weakened from their recent wars. It is the right time to expand the House of Islam into their wealthy possessions, forming a melting pot of cultures that will bring culture and science to new heights.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_TIBET</Tag>
		<Russian>It is the year 630 AD. The Tibetan clans around Lhasa have been united, and the current weakness of the neighboring Chinese Tang and Indian Pala empires opens the opportunity to expand your empire from the Tibetan highlands and spread Buddhist teaching in the whole world.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 630 AD. The Tibetan clans around Lhasa have been united, and the current weakness of the neighboring Chinese Tang and Indian Pala empires opens the opportunity to expand your empire from the Tibetan highlands and spread Buddhist teaching in the whole world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_KHMER</Tag>
		<Russian>655 год н.э. Нерегулярная природа муссонов Юго-восточной &#192;зии препятствовала развитию цивилизации в этом регионе до этого момента. Но теперь передовые методы управления водой кхмеров, способствующие быстрому росту населения и урбанизации, привели к основанию их столицы - &#192;нгкора.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 655 AD. The unpredictable nature of the South East Asian monsoons have so far prevented the formation of a developed civilization in the region. But now, the advanced Khmer water management techniques lead to the foundation of their capital Angkor, facilitating enormous population growth and urbanization.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_INDONESIA</Tag>
		<Russian>700 год н.э. Почти все торговые пути между Китаем и Индией проходят по Малаккскому проливу. Будучи расположенным на близлежащем острове Суматра, индонезийское царство Шривиджая становится главным центром торговли в юго-восточной &#192;зии.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 700 AD. Nearly all of the trade between China and India passes the Strait of Malacca. Benefiting from its position on the nearby island of Sumatra, the Indonesian Kingdom of Srivijaya rises to become a major trading power in Southeast Asia.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SPAIN</Tag>
		<Russian>718 год н.э. &#192;рабы из Халифата Омейядов завоевали почти всю Иберию и положили конец правлению вестготов. Теперь испанское королевство &#192;стурия, основанное на горном Севере, пытается восстановить управление христиан над Иберией и расширить его дальше.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 718 AD. Arabs from the Ummayad Caliphate have overrun almost all of Iberia and put an end to Visigoth rule. Now the Spanish Kingdom of Asturias is founded in the mountainous north, seeking to restore Christian control over Iberia and expand it beyond.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_SPAIN_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. The Spanish Empire is in a state of decline. Income from the American colonies is diminishing, the cultural flourishing of the last century has come to an end, and now the ruling Habsburg dynasty is about to die out. The conflict over the Spanish succession is about to consume Europe ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_FRANCE</Tag>
		<Russian>751 год н.э. После распада Западной Римской Империи, Империя Франков под руководством династии Меровингов стала крупнейшей христианской силой в Европе. С коронацией Пипина из династия Каролингов, франки ещ¸ на один шаг приблизились к восстановлению наследия Рима и доминированию в Христианской Европе.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 751 AD. After the collapse of the Western Roman Empire, the Merovingian Frankish Empire became the major Christian power in Europe. With the coronation of Pepin from the Carolingian dynasty, the Franks have come another step closer to reclaim Rome's legacy and dominate Christian Europe.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_FRANCE_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. France under the rule of Louis XIV is at the height of its power and the dominating cultural and military power in continental Europe. After extending its borders and winning the Thirty Years War, the impeding end of the Spanish Habsburgs presents another opportunity to expand French power.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ENGLAND</Tag>
		<Russian>829 год н.э. После переселения германских племен в Британию, остров разделился на несколько кельтских, норвежских и англо-саксонских королевств. Теперь же король Уэссекса был коронован как Бретвальда, то есть правитель всей &#192;нглии. После объединения, английский народ может начать править морями.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 829 AD. After the migration of Germanic peoples to Britain, the island has been divided between several Celtic, Norse and Anglo-Saxon kingdoms. Now the King of Wessex has been crowned Bretwalda and thus ruler of all of England. Now unified, the English people can turn their eyes from their island across the sea and gain rule of the waves.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ENGLAND_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. The Glorious Revolution has restored stability to the British thrones and paved the way to the Acts of Union. With its colonial holdings in the Americas and India growing, the British crown will be able to establish a world-wide empire and challenge the French dominance over Europe.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_HOLY_ROME</Tag>
		<Russian>843 год н.э. Верденский договор положил начало разделению Империи Франков на Западное и Восточное королевство франков. В восточной половине правили германские народы, а ее короли не только отказываются от романской культуры, но и считают свой императорский титул наследником Священной Римской Империи.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 843 AD. The Treaty of Verdun brings the final separation of the Frankish Empire into West and East Francia. The eastern half is dominated by German peoples, and not only would its German kings break with the Romantic Frankish culture, but also claim its imperial title and the continuation of the Holy Roman Empire.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_AUSTRIA_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Despite the setbacks during the Thirty Years War, the victory at the Siege of Vienna allowed the Habsburg Monarchy to drive back the Turks and secure their holdings in the Balkans. The beginning of the Austrian baroque let arts and architecture flourish, but the weakness of the Spanish line may lead to another war soon ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_RUSSIA</Tag>
		<Russian>860 год н.э. Варяжские торговцы Янтарного пути между Скандинавией и Византией начинают основывать на нем государства. Быстро смешавшись с их славянскими поддаными, они станут русскими и отправятся заселять огромные пространства Восточной Европы, а затем и дальше.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 860 AD. Varangian travelers among the amber road between Scandinavia and Byzantium begin to set up states along their routes. Quickly mingling with their Slavic subjects, they would become the Rus and set out to settle the vast areas of Eastern Europe and beyond.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_RUSSIA_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Under the rule of Peter the Great Russia is on the path of modernization. Sweden has just been defeated and the foundation of Sankt-Peterburg secured a window to the east for Russia. With the advance into Siberia, the Russian Empire is now the largest in the world.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NETHERLANDS</Tag>
		<Russian>1500 год н.э. Находящиеся на слиянии важнейших торговых путей Европы, Нидерланды являются самой насел¸нным и богатым регионом континента. Долгие века это богатсво шло иностранным владыкам, но теперь, после долгих войн, голландцы наконец добились независимости и установили Республику.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1581 AD. Situated at the confluence of Europe's most important trade routes, the Netherlands are the most populated and wealthiest region of the continent. Far too long this wealth has gone to foreign powers, but now, after long wars, the Dutch people have finally reached independence and established a Republic.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_NETHERLANDS_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Since their independence at the end of the Eighty Years war, the Netherlands have entered a Golden Age and become the European center of trade, industry, culture and science. This wealth however has created envy in the rising neighboring powers of France and Great Britain, and the Dutch will need to keep their colonial empire together to maintain their wealth.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MALI</Tag>
		<Russian>It is the year 989 AD. Sub-Saharan Africa is still underdeveloped compared to the rest of the old world. But the Mande people control rich gold mines, which has caught the attention of its northern neighbors. Defending against foreign attempts to seize its riches by force, Mali has now the opportunity to truly become the richest civilization on Earth.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 989 AD. Sub-Saharan Africa is still underdeveloped compared to the rest of the old world. But the Mande people control rich gold mines, which has caught the attention of its northern neighbors. Defending against foreign attempts to seize its riches by force, Mali has now the opportunity to truly become the richest civilization on Earth.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PORTUGAL</Tag>
		<Russian>1128 год. Португалия только что победила Испанию и обрела независимость. Находясь на западной оконечности Европы, королевство занимало отличное положение для отправки кораблей в порты по всему миру и контроля торговли всей Европы, &#192;фрики и &#192;зии.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1128 AD. Portugal has just defeated Spain and gained independence. Situated at the western end of Europe, the kingdom is in an excellent position to send ships to ports all over the world and control the trade of all of Europe, Africa and Asia.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_PORTUGAL_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. In the last century, Portugal has regained its independence from the Spanish crown. Many of its colonial possessions have been lost to the Dutch, but Brazil is still under Portuguese control and promises wealth for the future.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_INCA</Tag>
		<Russian>1150 год н.э. Манко Капак только что основал королевство Куско, первое королевство инков. Даже в суровых условиях &#192;ндов и при отсутствии подходящих стадных животных, им удалось создать империю, не виданную до тех пор в &#192;мериках.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1150 AD. Manco Capac has just founded the Kingdom of Cuzco, the first Incan kingdom. Even in the harsh environment of the Andes and lacking suitable pack animals, they set out to create an empire never seen before in the Americas.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ITALY</Tag>
		<Russian>1167 год. Италия слишком долго была под властью германских королей, но теперь города Ломбардии разцвели и, благодаря поддержке Папы, достигли де факто независимости. Итальянские города-государства, несмотря на частые междуусобицы, являются центрами науки, культуры и торговли, и могут использовать свои преимущества, чтобы начать Возрождение европейской культуры.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1167 AD. For too long has Italy been under the rule of German kings, but now the Lombard cities have risen up and thanks to Papal support, achieved de facto independence. The Italian city states, though often feuding with each other, are centers of science, culture and commerce and can now reap the benefits of their skills to usher in a Renaissance of European culture.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MONGOLIA</Tag>
		<Russian>1190 год. На протяжении веков народы монгольских степей были слишком сильно раздроблены, чтобы представлять реальную угрозу миру. Теперь же, когда Темуджину удалось объединить монгольские племена под своей властью, все изменилось. Вскоре и Восток, и Запад будут трепетать в страхе перед его армиями.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1190 AD. For centuries, the peoples of the Mongolian steppe were too divided to pose an actual threat to the world. Now that Temujin has managed to unify all Mongolian tribes under his command, everything has changed, and soon both Orient and Occident will tremble in fear before his armies.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_AZTECS</Tag>
		<Russian>1195 год н.э. &#192;цтеки основали город Теночтитлан на озере Тескоко в долине Мехико. Благодаря разумному использованию систем орошения, Теночтитлан стал стал самым крупным городом Мезоамерики и стал властвовать над окружающими городами.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1195 AD. The Aztec peoples have founded the city of Tenochtitlan at Lake Texcoco in the Valley of Mexico. Through clever use of irrigation systems, Tenochtitlan can become the largest metropolis of Mesoamerica and dominate the surrounding cities.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MUGHALS</Tag>
		<Russian>1260 год н.э. Хотя мусульманские правители время от времени совершали набеги на Индию на протяжении веков, основание Султаната Дели Мухамед Гури ознаменовало превращение ислама в политическую силу на субконтиненте. Их наследники, в том числе мусульманская династия Моголов, распространили ислам по всей Индии и воздвигли величайшие чудеса архитектуры.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1206 AD. Although Muslim rulers have occasionally raided India for centuries, the foundation of the Delhi Sultanate by Muhammad of Ghor marks the establishment of Islam as a political power on the subcontinent. Their successors, including the Muslim Mughal dynasty, would spread their faith all over India and erect its greatest architectural wonders since ancient times.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MUGHALS_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. The Mughal Empire has reached its zenith. While culture and architecture are still thriving, Mughal hegemony over India is threatened by the emergence of a sovereign Hindu state in the Marathas and the gains of various European powers on India's coasts.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_TURKEY</Tag>
		<Russian>1280 год н.э. После распада Империи сульджуков, турки &#192;натолии разделены на несколько небольших бейликов. Однако, сама Византия также ослаблена, а бейлик Османли находится в руках сильного лидера, поэтому создание турецкой Османской Империи уже близко. Захватив Босфор, они могут создать империю, раскинувшуюся на три континента.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1280 AD. After the collapse of the Seljuk Empire, the Anatolian Turks are divided into several small Beyliks. However, Byzantium is weakened itself, and now that the Osmanli Beylik is in the hands of a strong leader, a Turkish Ottoman Empire seems close. With the Bosphorus right within their grasp, they have the opportunity to form an empire that stretches over three continents.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_TURKEY_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. With the defeat at the Siege of Vienna, the military expansion of the Ottoman Empire has come to an end and it is on the defensive against the growing power of Austria and Russia. This change in the balance of power leads to increased cultural contact and exchange with the Europeans and a flowering of Ottoman culture.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_THAILAND</Tag>
		<Russian>1350 год н.э. Коллапс Империи кхмеров позволил тайским народам главенствовать в Юго-восточной &#192;зии. Им удалось разрушить столицу кхмеров &#192;нгкор и основать к западу от него свое собственное царство &#192;юттхая.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1350 AD. The collapse of the Khmer Empire has allowed the Thai people to claim hegemony over South East Asia. They were able to raze the Khmer capital of Angkor and found their own kingdom west of it, in Ayutthaya.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_THAILAND_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. With excellent relations with the new European powers in South Asia and controlling one of the largest cities in the world, the Kingdom of Ayutthaya is in an advantageous condition. However, the threat from their Burmese neighbors is beginning to grow and even the Europeans might consider colonization ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_GERMANY</Tag>
		<Russian>1701 год н.э. После заключения Вестфальского мира в 1648 году, Священная Римская Империя превратилась в рыхлое объединение государств. Хотя власть Императора сосредоточена в его австрийских владениях, электорат Бранденбурга-Пруссии провозгласил себя королем Пруссии, стремясь объединить германскую нацию под своей властью.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1701 AD. Since the Westphalian Peace of 1648, the Holy Roman Empire is nothing but a loose organization of states. While the power of the Emperor concentrates in his Austrian holdings, the Electorate of Brandenburg-Prussia elevated itself to the Kingdom of Prussia, seeking to unite the German nation under its own hegemony.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_AMERICA</Tag>
		<Russian>1776 год н.э. Уставшие от зарубежной власти, народы американских колоний начали революцию, чтобы создать свою собственную нацию. Но их молодая республика все еще находидся под угрозой завоевания европейскими колониальными державами и должна превзойти своих бывших хозяев, чтобы исполнить свою предначертание.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1776 AD. Discontent with foreign domination, the people in the American colonies have risen up in revolution to found their own nation. However, their fledgling republic is still in danger of being reclaimed by European colonial powers and has to surpass its former masters to fulfill its manifest destiny.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_TAMILS</Tag>
		<Russian>300 год до н.э. С развитием литературы Сангама, на юге Индии возникает культура тамилов. Их положение, близкое и к Китаю, и к Риму, а также доступном ценных специй делают местные династии Чераз, Пандья и Чола богатыми центрами торговли.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 300 BC. With the development of their Sangam literature, the Tamil culture rises to the south of India. Their position close to both China and Rome as well as the availability of valuable spices have made the local dynasties of the Cheras, Pandyans and Cholas affluent centers of trade.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_TAMILS_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Since the decline of the Vijayanagara Empire in the 16th century, the Kingdom of Mysore has been the dominant power in the southern Deccan, resisting Mughal expansion. With the appearance of the Marathas and the British, the power structure in India has shifted, requiring Mysore to defend its sovereignty again.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_MOORS</Tag>
		<Russian>711 год. Берберы и арабы Магриба пересекли Гиблартар, нанесли порожение вестготам и создали эмират Кордоба в &#192;ль-&#192;ндалусе, изгнав иберийских христиан к северному побережью &#192;стурии.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 711 AD. The Berbers and Arabs of the Maghreb have crossed the Strait of Gibraltar and defeated the Visigoths to establish the Emirate of Cordoba in Al-Andalus, driving the Iberian Christians to the northern coast of Asturias.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_POLAND</Tag>
		<Russian>1025 год. После крещения западных славян в 966 году, первый польский правитель был коронован в качестве короля. Плодородные земли благоприятны для роста городов, а соседи-язычники на севере и приходящие в упадок православные государства на востоке представляют возможности для экспансии.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1025 AD. After the Christianization of the West Slavs in 966, the first Polish ruler is coronated as king. Fertile lands promise urban growth, while pagan neighbors to the north and declining Orthodox polities to the east offer opportunities for expansion.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_POLAND_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Cossack uprisings and the Swedish deluge have severely weakened the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, and the decentralized political system is incapable of reform. Encircled by the growing powers of Prussia, Austria and Russia, the very independence of Poland is in danger ...</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CONGO</Tag>
		<Russian>1390 год. Королевство Конго возникло возникло в результате объединения нескольких племенных государств в дельте реги Конго именно в тот момент, когда Европейские державы начали расширять свое влияние в &#192;фрике. Ему предстоит сохранить независимость и религиозными, и политическими средствами.</Russian>
		<English>It is the year 1390 AD. The Kingdom of Kongo emerges after the unification of several tribal polities in the Congo delta just when European powers start to expand their influence in Africa. It must try to keep its independence by both religious and economic means.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CONGO_1700AD</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1700 AD. Continued warfare with the Portuguese and internal rebellions have weakened the Kingdom of Kongo to the point of effective colonization. The kingdom is still lagging behind scientifically and economically, and often the slave trade remains as the only viable source of income.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_ARGENTINA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1810 AD. Spurred by the weakness of the Spanish Empire and the ideals of the French Revolution, the people in the Viceroyalty of the Rio de la Plata have overthrown their viceroy and started a revolution to form the Argentine Republic.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_BRAZIL</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1822 AD. After the revolution in Portugal threatens Brazilian sovereignty with in the United Kingdom, Dom Pedro of Brazil declares an independent empire. Brazil's rich plantations as well as the Amazon rainforest promise wealth for the future, but also demand preservation.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_DOM_CANADA</Tag>
		<English>It is the year 1867. After the American revolution, Canada has remained under colonial control. With the approval of the North America Acts, Canada has now been finally granted independence so it can expand across the Great White North on its own accord.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
